Rebecca Adamson Papers, 1979-2007
Sophia Smith Collection
Rebecca Adamson papers
1978-2007 (ongoing)
Adamson, Rebecca, 1949-
MS 481
54 boxes (30.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Economist, Founder First Nations Development Institute, Native American rights advocate. Papers are primarily related to her professional and public life, and focus on two organizations founded by Adamson, the First Nations Development Institute (FNDI) and First Peoples Worldwide (FPW). Major topics include American Indians, indigenous people, and economic development. Portions of the work of FNDI are particularly well chronicled through detailed staff reports and records on Field Operations and the Lakota Fund. Speeches, writings, and interviews elucidate the development of Adamson's "financial sufficiency approach" to economic development and her conception of "indigenous economics" as a model for sustainable development. Conference, meetings, and organizations files document Adamson's active involvement in a wide variety of national and international gatherings, organizations, and boards.
Rebecca Adamson was born in Akron, Ohio in 1949 to Barbara Crytz Hendrix and Robert Paul Adamson. Barbara Hendrix Adamson was Cherokee and Robert Adamson was of Swedish descent. Rebecca spent summers near Lumberton in the Smoky Mountains of North Carolina with her maternal grandparents, from whom she learned Indian ways and values, at the Qualla reservation. After graduating from Firestone High School in Akron in 1967, she studied philosophy at the University of Akron and then took courses in law and economics at Piedmont College in Georgia. At twenty, she dropped out and spent much of the 1970s working on Indian reservations west of the Mississippi River where "many young, college-educated Native Americans from cities were joining forces with those who had preserved traditional ways." 1
Adamson first went to work for the Nez Perce in Idaho helping to find money for economic development projects. In 1970 she began working for the Coalition of Indian Controlled School Boards in Denver and became its director of field programs in 1972. The Coalition worked to "wrest control of Indian schools from the U.S. government and Christian religious groups that had been running them for more than 100 years."2 It was a system that took Indian children from their families and sent them to boarding schools where they were forced to assimilate and were often abused.
The Coalition's work led directly to passage of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act in 1975, giving American Indians the right to run their own schools, agencies, and programs, though the U.S. Government retained financial control. But the economic situation Adamson observed, "virtually no private sector…. Government…the dominant employer, poverty the reigning industry, welfare the surest means of support,"3 convinced her that "reservation tribes needed a similar voice in their economic growth."4
She was married for several years to Denny Hurtado, a Native American activist of the Skokomish Tribe, with whom she had a daughter, Neva, in 1975. They separated in 1977 and divorced in tribal court by 1979.
From 1976 to 1979 Adamson worked as a free-lance consultant traveling from project to project helping to develop tribal business skills. During this time, her marriage dissolved, her brother died of a painful illness, her lover was killed in a hunting accident, she was diagnosed with uterine cancer, and she lost her job. "I was sitting in bed and couldn't move, and my 3-year old daughter brought me an aspirin and a glass of water, and I thought, 'I've got to get it together.' If you stay inside yourself, you only go deeper and deeper."5
After moving back east to live with her parents, Adamson cashed her last unemployment check and went to New York City to seek funding for her proposal to establish a "Financial Self-Sufficiency Project" to support culturally appropriate economic development among American Indians. The first funder to respond was Susan Berresford at the Ford Foundation. With the resulting $25,000 grant, Adamson launched First Nations Financial Project in 1980 (re-named First Nations Development Institute in 1990) in Fredericksburg, Virginia, an organization that makes grants and loans, provides technical expertise, and does policy advocacy.
At the core of Adamson's work is the "financial sufficiency approach" in which profit is not the only factor considered in economic development. She insists that economic development must also consider human and cultural elements.
The initial grant allowed Adamson to field test her "financial sufficiency approach" through a pilot project on the Pine Ridge Reservation in South Dakota, the poorest place in the United States. A traveling exhibit of artwork by reservation children raised about $20,000 and allowed the Little Wound School to purchase necessities like warm winter coats. The funding also supported a study of the reservation economy by graduate student Richard Sherman. His work revealed that eighty-five per cent of the reservation's gross income was spent in border towns off the reservation, but also identified a vibrant informal economic sector made up of home-based businesses on the reservation. These businesses had no access to capital for expansion through traditional banks and other financing institutions, so First Nations Development Institute (FNDI) worked to establish a microenterprise loan fund. The Lakota Fund, established in 1986, was one of the first such loan funds in the U.S. It provided technical assistance and small loans to new and existing businesses on Pine Ridge Reservation. Once the Fund was firmly established in 1992, it became an independent organization.
FNDI's methods seek answers from within Native American communities as opposed to imposing solutions from the outside. FNDI's projects "build on a tribe's unique culture and resources at hand to work toward a more stable economic future."6 Interviewed for the Fredericksburg, Virginia, Free-Lance Star in 1995, Adamson declared: "I want to show the brilliance, the creativity, the efficacy of Indian people."
One of Adamson's primary critiques of the government's approach to economic development on Indian reservations is its insistence on bringing inappropriately sized (and therefore unsustainable) projects to reservations. Her focus is on small and local, "economically do-able" projects which "grow the grassroots talents living on reservations." FNDI pursues these aims without any funding from the U.S. government.
Over the years, FNDI's efforts have combined national, state, and local policy advocacy; research; direct access to funding through loans and grants; technical assistance; and educational programs. The organization's work led in 1994 to passage of the American Indian Trust Fund Management Reform Act, and the Reigle Community Development and Regulatory Improvement Act which established the Community Development Financial Institutions Fund.
By the mid-1990s, Adamson began to turn her attention to struggles of indigenous peoples elsewhere in the world, particularly those related to land ownership, self-government, economic viability, and cultural preservation. The result was First Peoples Worldwide which originated as an international project of FNDI in 1996 and became a separate organization in 2007.
Beyond fostering self-sufficiency, Adamson contends that indigenous communities have much to teach the rest of the world about an economy of "enoughness." "We can never create an economy that's sustainable if we focus only on accumulation and growth, and don't focus on how to share the wealth."7 "Indian people are natural systems thinkers. We understand the interrelatedness of problems and can therefore design holistic solutions."8
Adamson earned a M.S. in economic development from New Hampshire College (now known as University of Southern New Hampshire), and developed and taught a graduate course on Indigenous Economics as part of its Community Economic Development Program.
Adamson has served as advisor to the United Nations on Rural Development, as the U.S. delegate to the United Nations International Labor Organization for International Indigenous Rights, as an advisor to the U.S. Catholic Conference's Campaign for Human Development, and as a consultant on Aboriginal development to the Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development in Australia.
In the corporate sector, Adamson has been a member of the Boards of Directors for the Calvert Social Investment Fund, a socially responsible mutual fund, the Calvert Foundation Board, and Tom's of Maine. She also co-founded the Calvert High Social Impact Investments, the first financial instrument whereby mutual fund shareholders and other individuals invest in community development loan funds. She is an advisor to the International Council on Mining and Metals (ICMM) and to the International Petroleum Industry Environmental Conservation Association (IPIECA).
Adamson has served in the non-profit sector on the Board of Governors for Indiana University's Center on Philanthropy, the Board of Directors for Corporation for Enterprise Development, the Bay Foundation, the Josephine Bay Paul and C. Michael Paul Foundation, the Bridgespan Group, the Board of Directors for the National Committee for Responsive Philanthropy, the Council on Foundations Management and Investment Committee, the President's Council on Sustainable Development/Sustainable Communities Task Force, Independent Sector, the Ms. Foundation for Women, The Natural Step, and Earthday Network 2000.
She has been a member of the editorial boards of Indian Country Today, Native Americas, and for Akwe:kon Journal.
She was a founding member of Native Americans in Philanthropy, Funders Who Fund Native Americans, and International Funders for Indigenous Peoples.
In 1997 the Council on Foundations honored Adamson with its Scrivner Award for creative and innovative grant making and she was also the Ms. Foundation's Woman of the Year. She was named one of the top ten Social Entrepreneurs of the Year by Who Cares Magazine in 1998. In 2001 she received the Independent Sector's John W. Gardner Leadership Award. She was selected by the Virginia Foundation for Women as one of eight Virginia Women in History honorees in 2002. She was the 2003 National Women's History Month Honoree. In 2004 Adamson received a Doctorate in Humane Letters from Dartmouth College and the Schwab Foundation named her an Outstanding Social Entrepreneur. Adamson is featured in the 2013 PBS documentary Makers: Women Who Make America.
Sources
1. Ridley, Kimberly, "Indian Giver," HOPE Magazine, June 1997
2. Ridley, "Indian Giver," HOPE Magazine, June 1997
3. Margolis, Richard J., "America's New Entrepreneurs," The New Leader, 30 Nov 1987
4. "1970s 'visionary' now helping Indians take control," Richmond Times-Dispatch, 20 Jan 1997
5. Batz, Jeannette, "First Efforts," Riverfront Times, 19-25 March 1997
6. First Nations Financial Project brochure, undated
7. Ridley, "Indian Giver," HOPE Magazine, June 1997
8. Ford Foundation REPORT, spring 1997
The Rebecca Adamson Papers consist of 20.75 linear ft. and are primarily related to her professional and public life, dating from 1979 to 2007. Types of materials include audiovisual materials, correspondence, datebooks, financial records, minutes, speeches, photographs, press releases, program files, publications, reports, journal and newspaper articles, subject files, artifacts, and memorabilia.
The bulk of the papers date from 1982 to 2007 and focus on two organizations founded by Adamson, First Nations Development Institute and First Peoples Worldwide. There is little personal material. Major topics found throughout these papers include American Indians, indigenous people, and economic development.
Portions of the work of FNDI are particularly well chronicled through detailed staff reports and records on Field Operations and the Lakota Fund. Trip itineraries and research notes document the hard work of raising funds to support First Nations' efforts.
In addition to the First Nations files, speeches, writings, and interviews elucidate the development of Adamson's "financial sufficiency approach" to economic development and her conception of "indigenous economics" as a model for sustainable development.
Records in Series II. Conferences and Meetings and Series IV. Organization Files document Adamson's active involvement in a wide variety of national and international gatherings, organizations, and boards.
ACRONYMS
ANA = Administration for Native Americans (US Dept of Health and Human Services)
ATNI = Affiliated Tribes of Northwest Indians
CFED = Corporation for Enterprise Development
CTUIR = Confederated Tribes of the Umatilla Indian Reservation
FNDI = First Nations Development Institute
FNFP = First Nations Financial Project
HEAP = Human Economics in Action Program
KANA = Kodiak Area Native Association
NAP = Native Americans in Philanthropy
OEDP = Overall Economic Development Program
PRI = Program Related Investment
REIS = Reservation Economic Impact Study
TCEMP = Tribal Commerce and Enterprise Management Program
TCEP = Tribal Commerce and Enterprise Program
USET = United South and Eastern Tribes
WELRP = White Earth Land Recovery Project (Winona La Duke -Minnesota)
Oweesta = money (Mohawk)
Tiyospaye = extended family (Lakota)
This collection is organized into nine series:
I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
II. CONFERENCES AND MEETINGS
III. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES
IV. ORGANIZATION FILES
V. PHOTOGRAPHS
VI. SPEECHES AND WRITINGS
VII. SUBJECT FILES
VIII. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS AND COMPUTER MEDIA
IX. ARTIFACTS AND MEMORABILIA
OVERSIZE MATERIALS
SERIES III. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES--RESTRICTED MATERIALS
With the exception of a small number of Dakota Fund loan application files, the Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Periodic additions to this collection are expected and may not be reflected in this record.
Rebecca Adamson donated her Papers to the Sophia Smith Collection beginning in 2003.
Processed by Maida Goodwin, Skyler Lawton, and Tiffany Peterson.
Businesswomen -- United States -- Biography -- Sources; Economic development -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Indians of North America -- Economic conditions -- 20th century -- Sources; Indians of North America -- Politics and government -- 20th century -- Sources; Indians of North America -- Social conditions -- 20th century -- Sources; Indian business enterprises -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Indian reservations -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Indian women -- United States -- Biography -- Sources; Self-determination, National -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Adamson, Rebecca, 1949-; First Nations Development Institute (Fredericksburg, VA) -- History
Related materials can be found in the Coalition of Indian Controlled School Boards Oral History Project.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS 1982-2001, undated, 1.25 linear ft.
  This small series provides an overview of Rebecca Adamson's work from around the time of the founding of First Nations Development Institute in 1979-80 to the early 2000s. Datebooks and the chronological file give a sense of her extensive travel and involvement in a wide variety of organizations, meetings, and conferences. There is a small amount of personal correspondence.
- SERIES II. CONFERENCES AND MEETINGS 1988-2001, undated, .5 linear ft.
  This series contains correspondence, publications, reports, agendas, conference packets, and notes from a wide variety of conferences and meetings Adamson attended. Materials related to speeches Adamson gave at conferences and meetings can be found in SERIES VII. SPEECHES AND WRITINGS and SERIES IX. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS.
- SERIES III. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES circa 1979-2007, undated, 13.5 linear ft.
  By far the largest series, Professional Activities is divided into two subseries: First Nations Development Institute and First Peoples Worldwide. FNDI materials consist of extensive files from the organization founded by Rebecca Adamson as First Nations Financial Project in 1979. Included are correspondence, financial and fundraising records, program materials, publications, newspaper clippings, minutes, reports, events files, and policy materials. Of particular interest are extensive staff reports dating from the early 1980s to the early 1990s, the files on Field Operations, and on the establishment of the Lakota Fund.
  First Peoples Worldwide subseries contains materials related to the origins of the organization as an international project of FNDI, and its subsequent separation from FNDI in 2007. The materials primarily consist of correspondence, but there are also some minutes, fundraising materials, and files related to Adamson's travel.
- SERIES IV. ORGANIZATION FILES 1977-2002, undated, 4.75 linear ft
  This series contains files on other organizations Adamson has been associated with in some way. Included are some of the many organizations for which Adamson has served on the Board or an advisory committee. Materials include correspondence, handbooks, meeting packets, minutes, proposals, publications, and reports.
- SERIES V. PHOTOGRAPHS 1991-93, undated, .5 linear ft.
  This series consists of prints, negatives, and color transparencies. The bulk of the images are related to First Nations Arts, FNDI's program to market American Indian arts and crafts. In addition, there are images taken at some FNDI workshops. There are also a few photographs of Adamson, her family, and personal travel.
- SERIES VI. SPEECHES AND WRITINGS1982-2001, .75 linear ft.
  This series contains correspondence, texts, programs, conference reports, and news clippings related to speeches and articles authored by Adamson. Video and audio of some Adamson speeches can be found in SERIES X. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS.
- SERIES VII. SUBJECT FILES1941-2001, undated, 2.25 linear ft.
  This series consists of clippings, publications, scholarly articles, and reports on subjects of interest to Adamson. Most pertain to American Indians, indigenous peoples, and economic development.
- SERIES VIII. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS AND COMPUTER MEDIA1986-2004, undated, 3.75 linear ft.
  This series contains audiotapes, videotapes, compact disks, digital video disks, and other digital files. Included are Rebecca Adamson interviews, speeches, and award presentations; videotapes of FNDI meetings, seminars, and conferences; video related to economic development projects funded by FNDI; training and informational video related to Indians and banking and economic development. In addition, there are computer disks containing FNDI office files.
  Original audiovisual materials are closed to research. Researchers interested in accessing audiovisual materials for which there is no extant use copy should contact the Sophia Smith Collection to discuss options.
- SERIES IX. ARTIFACTS AND MEMORABILIA1995, undated, .5 linear ft.
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS, .5 linear ft.
- RESTRICTED MATERIALS1987-92, .25 linear ft.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - Clippings, 1985-87, 1994-2001, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
  - Address book undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Awards and honors
    - General 1994-97 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - John W. Gardner Leadership Award, Independent Sector 2001 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Honorary degree, Dartmouth College 2004 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Business cards and rolodex undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chronological file 1998-2002 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Correspondence 1988, 1993-2005, undated (Box 1, Folder 13-15)
  - Datebooks
    - 1982-84, 1986-95, 1997-98, 2000-02 (Box 2, Folder 1-12)
    - 2003-05 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Family: Neva Adamson 1993, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous 1993-2000, undated (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
  - New Hampshire College, Community Economic Development Program: course notes 1993 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - University of Alaska, Indigenous Economics course 2001 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- SERIES II. CONFERENCES AND MEETINGS, [see also Series VI. SPEECHES AND WRITINGS]
  - General 1988 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - International Labour Conference 1988 (Box 3, Folder 8-11)
  - National Symposium on Native American Enterprise Zone Development 26-28 1990 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - "Defining Sustainable Communities," Tides Foundation 2-4 Jun 1994 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - The Bioneers: Practical Solutions for Restoring the Earth 25-27 Oct 1996 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - White House Conversation with Women Leaders on Race 6 Feb 1998 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Socially Responsible Investing in the Rockies 2-5 Oct 1999 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - White House Conference on Philanthropy 22 Oct 1999 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Lifebridge Foundation Grantee Gathering Aug 2000 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - "Imagine Peace," Women's Peace Conference 25 Feb 2001 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - "Biodiversity and Indigenous Peoples: Donor Best Practices Supporting Civil and Conservation," roundtable and workshop, Copenhagen, Denmark 9 Mar 2001 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - World Business Council for Sustainable Development meeting May 2001 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Council on Foundations Fall Conference 2001 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "Global Ethics for a Humane World," virtual conference 10-15 Dec 2001 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- SERIES III. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES, [See also Restricted materials in box 51]
  - First Nations Development Institute
    - General and history
      - General circa 1979-circa 1994, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Clippings 1980-2001, undated (Box 4, Folder 5-8)
      - Financial Sufficiency Model circa 1983, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - "Organizational Chart and Narrative" circa 1985 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Organization and growth and development charts 1979-91, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Paper on FNDI by Jan Seago 1996 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - "A Study of Traditional and Informal Sector Micro-Enterprise Activity and Its Impact on the Pine Ridge Indian Reservation Economy," a research paper by Richard T. Sherman 1988 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Impact evaluation by the Stevens Group, 1991
        - Progress report 7 Feb (Box 4, Folder 14)
        - A Plan to Measure Past and Future Impact of FNFP, Jun (Box 4, Folder 15)
        - Selected readings on economic impact (Box 4, Folder 16)
      - Management reference manual 22 Jul 1988 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Organizational assessment by Brody & Weisner 1991 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Board circa 1986-92 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Conferences and workshops
      - Micro-Credit workshop Jan 1989 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - "New Directions and Lessons Learned: Reservation-Based Lending and Investment Management," co-sponsored by FNFP and National Federation of Community Development Credit Unions 1988-89 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Tribal Financial Management workshop 1990 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Roundtable on Indigenous Economics, hosted by Aspen Institute and FNDI Oct 1991 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence
      - General 1983-2001 (Box 5, Folder 8-9)
      - AIComm [email service] 1986-87 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - American Indian newspapers 1981-83, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - American Indian Scholarships, Inc. 1986 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Ben and Jerry's 1990 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Henry J. Kaiser Family Foundation 1996 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - Interfaith Center on Corporate Responsibility (ICCR) 2000-01 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - National Indian Gaming Association 2000-01 (Box 5, Folder 16)
      - Office correspondence 1988 (Box 5, Folder 17)
        - 1989-2006 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - Eagle Staff Fund
      - General 1997-2001 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Grantee: Council of Athabascan Tribal Governments (CATG) 1997 (Box 6, Folder 4)